Finding Aid for William Perdue Halstead papers, 1935-1975
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
William Perdue Halstead papers 1935-1975
Halstead, William Perdue.
921107 Aa 2
Professor of speech communication and theatre at the University of Michigan. Correspondence and other materials relating in part to his interest in university theatre productions.
5 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The papers were donated by Mrs. William P. Halstead (donor no. 3190 ). The bulk of the collection came to the library in 1991-1992. Additional materials were acquired in 2007.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
William P. Halstead's career spanned five decades at the University of Michigan as a Professor of Speech Communication and Theatre. Halstead was born on February 10, 1906 in Terre Haute, Indiana. He received his A.B. from Indiana University and after pursuing graduate studies at a number of universities, completed his Ph.D. at Michigan in 1935. He started his career at Michigan as a student teacher, then became an instructor upon completion of his doctorate. In 1937 Halstead was promoted to assistant professor, to associate professor in 1942, and to professor in 1952. During his long career at the university, Halstead played a key role in theatre activities as a stage director and a teacher, particularly in the field of theatre history. He served as chairman of the theatre department from 1956 to 1973 and it was under his guidance and inspiration that the department achieved the signal feat of producing all the Shakespeare plays. Halstead retired from the university in May 1975.
Nationally, Halstead was very active in the American Educational Theatre Association, serving as executive secretary from 1952 to 1949 and as president in 1952-53. He co-authored a book on directing. Professor Halstead's last academic achievement was completing the 12-volume work Shakespeare as Spoken with publishing completed in 1979. Two supplemental volumes were published in 1983. The work is a collation of all acting editions and all prompt books of Shakespeare's works.
William P. Halstead died December 31, 1983.
The William P. Halstead papers consist of correspondence, clippings, theater programs and other materials relating to his work in the Speech Department and to his interest in university theater productions. (Halstead bound most of his papers in chronological order. The bound volumes and additional unbound materials are separated into five series: Personal, Production Materials, University of Michigan, Department of Speech, Miscellaneous, and Photographs.
Subjects:
Halstead, William Perdue.; Theater--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Speech.; University of Michigan--Dramatics.; University of Michigan--Faculty.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Halstead, William Perdue.; Indiana University--Students.; Theatrical productions.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Albums.
- Personal, bound volumes
  The Personal volumes document Halstead's career and activities at the University of Michigan during the years 1935-1975. Included in the volumes are correspondence, theater programs, lectures, news clippings, articles, and other miscellaneous materials.
  - Lectures, Community Centennial Banquet, and Miscellaneous 1935-1938 (Box 1)
  - Lectures, Radio, and Speeches 1938-1940 (Box 1)
  - Army 1942-1946 (Box 1)
    (contains photographs)
    - Army 1942-1943 (Box 1)
    - Army 1944-1946 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous 1945-1975 (Box 1)
    - 1945-1951 (Box 1)
    - 1951-1952 (Box 1)
    - 1951-1954 (Box 1)
    - 1952-1956 (Box 1)
    - 1956-1958 (Box 1)
    - Speeches and Introductions 1956-1958 (Box 1)
    - 1955-1959 (Box 1)
    - 1958-1959 (Box 1)
    - 1959-1960 (Box 1)
    - 1960-1962 (Box 1)
    - circa 1963 (Box 1)
    - 1964 (Box 1)
    - 1963-1966 (Box 1)
    - 1964-1965 (Box 1)
    - 1966-1967 (Box 2)
    - 1966-1968, 2 volumes (Box 2)
    - 1966-1968 (Box 2)
    - 1968-1969 (Box 2)
    - 1970-1975, 2 volumes (Box 2)
- Production Materials, bound volumes
  The Production Materials volumes contain programs, stage instructions, tryout record forms, and notations on the production. Also included is a small amount of press coverage of various productions.
  - Coriolanus, 1966 (Box 2)
  - The Country Wife, The Would be Gentleman 1967 (Box 2)
  - Cymbeline (Box 2)
  - Henry VI, 2 volumes (Box 2)
  - Love's Labor's Lost, 1958 (Box 2)
  - Pericles, 1974 (Box 2)
  - The Servant of Two Masters, 2 volumes (Box 3)
  - Timon of Athens, 1971 (Box 3)
  - Titus Andronicus, 1969 (Box 3)
  - Various Productions Press: Coverage and Programs (Box 3)
- University of Michigan, Department of Speech
  The University of Michigan, Department of Speech series includes records related to Halstead's role as a business manager and financial record keeper within the department. Also included are teaching materials that Halstead used in his courses.
  - Attendance Figures and Box Office Audits (Box 3)
  - Correspondence of Business Manager (William Halstead) 1939-1941 (Box 3)
  - Financial Records Related to Assistantships (Box 3)
  - "Organization and Instruction" Booklet (Box 3)
  - Playlists 1928-1975 (Box 3)
  - Teaching Materials
    - 17th Century Theater (Box 3)
    - 19th Century Theater (Box 3)
    - 20th Century Theater Companies (Box 3)
    - American Theater Organizations (Box 3)
    - Ancient Theater (Box 3)
    - Appia (Box 3)
    - Artaud (Box 3)
    - Elizabethan Theater (Box 3)
    - Free Theaters (Box 3)
    - General History of Theater (Box 3)
    - Gordon Craig (Box 3)
    - Greek Theater (Box 3)
    - History of Theater in the United States (Box 4)
    - Max Reinhardt (Box 4)
    - Meiningen (Box 4)
    - National Theaters (Box 4)
    - Perspective (Box 4)
    - Revolutionary Russians (Box 4)
    - Roman Theaters (Box 4)
    - Speech (Box 4)
    - Stanislavsky (Box 4)
    - Various, 4 folders (Box 4)
    - Voice and Diction (Box 4)
  - University Players Guild (Box 4)
- Miscellaneous
  The Miscellaneous volumes series includes an omnibus volume containing incoming and outgoing correspondence with theatre people. The other volume in the series contains correspondence on the finishing of the Shakespeare Canon and notes on Halstead's retirement. The unbound materials in this series include additional correspondence, resumes, and published works and presentations by Halstead.
  - Correspondence about Shakespeare Canon (Box 4)
  - Curriculum Vitas and Resumes (Box 4)
  - Materials on finishing Shakespeare Canon and notes on retirement 1974-1975 (Box 4)
  - Omnibus (mostly correspondence) 1950s (Box 4)
  - Passports and Identity Cards (Box 4)
  - Published Works, Presentations, and Reports (Box 4)
- Photographs
  The Photographs series consist of images of Halstead's family, his travels, and his years at Indiana University. Also included are some loose images of theatrical productions in which he participated.
  - 1921-circa 1926 (Box 5)
  - 1923-1927 Indiana University (Box 5)
  - 1928-circa 1952 (Box 5)
  - 1930 European Trip (Box 5)
  - Personal (Box 5)
  - Theatrical Productions (Box 5)